most people understand that usually it
takes a great deal of personal sacrifice
to become worldclass at a skill but the
thing is this belief often serves as an
excuse for people to not give their
utmost effort to achieving their goals
and over the years I've seen this
pattern repeatedly with people learning
to trade since they think there's a huge
cost in giving it their 100% effort they
just settle for mediocrity instead they
go through the motions trading aimlessly
each day hoping they'll magically
improve practicing things at a leisurely
pace and learning only the things that
seem most interesting to them but
there's an irony here that most people
don't realize so I was looking through
my notes the other day and I came across
these questions from James CLE have a
think about them and try to answer them
in relation to how you approach your
trading development in other words the
things that you choose to learn how you
approach your practice sessions and how
you focus on leveling up your trading
performance in general what's the cost
of doing a poor job what's the cost of
doing a mediocre job what's the cost of
doing an exceptional job which price are
you willing to pay so for example some
of the costs involved in doing an
exceptional job are time effort
discipline and discomfort and this often
means also making other sacrifices to
free up that necessary time and energy
and these are usually the exact reasons
why most people don't do an exceptional
job because they're just not willing to
pay those costs so they avoid learning
difficult topics they stay in their
comfort zone rather than addressing
their weaknesses and working on those
they focus on the fun parts of trading
and avoid the tedious but necessary
aspects whether consciously or not they
believe there's an easier path that
requires less of them they don't need a
structured and focused learning approach
they don't need to work hard with
urgency they can just keep things laid
back and they'll get there eventually
but let's think for a second about what
it means to do a poor job or mediocre
job what are the costs it might seem
like the costs are lower than doing an
exceptional job but ironically you're
actually more likely to incur much
greater costs let me explain so ever
since I was a kid I've always had at
least one guitar nearby in a bedroom
living room or office and when I was at
college and university I was really
dedicated with my guitar playing I spent
at least a couple of hours every day
playing the guitar it had nothing to do
with my degree but truth be told I was
just certain I was going to be a rockar
spoiler alert I wasn't now across that
6-year period 2 years at College 4 years
at University I estimate that I spent a
total of at least 4 to 5,000 hours
playing guitar and I improved
significantly I went from being able to
play relatively simple songs at the
start of that period to being able to
shred and Avenge Sevenfold solo but then
I graduated and started my job in
banking and suddenly I didn't have as
much time as I did before when I was at
University so I had to prioritize my
spare time and playing guitar just
wasn't as much of a priority as other
things like trading or going out so over
the 14 years that have followed since I
left University I've been really
inconsistent most days I don't play at
all and only occasionally I'll go
through a week or two where I get back
into it I'm more motivated and I'm more
consistent so I estimate that over these
14 years I've played the guitar for for
around 1,500 to 2,000 hours and how much
has my playing improved during that time
it hasn't it's got worse much worse it's
cost me time and effort but I haven't
seen any Improvement but if I spent that
same amount of time in a more focused
effortful and consistent way my skill
level would have continued to improve
dramatically I could have spent the same
amount of time but achieved much greater
results and this is exactly what most
people do with their trading they invest
the time but their effort and Direction
just isn't there and then we have the
mental aspect when you're mentally
invested in a goal or a dream the more
time that passes Without You achieving
it the more negatively it affects you
psychologically you'll experience
frustration disillusionment and even
lower self-esteem you see we all have
this intrinsic drive to get better at
the things we do and when we achieve a
small Improvement a gain a success or a
win we produce dopamine this is our
brain's way to push us to take action
take risks and seek new grounds so when
we work on something that's important to
us like trading and we make progress our
dopamine levels Spike and a series of
these spikes each day is what gives us
that inner feeling of momentum that
feeling that you have of having momentum
is just a series of dopamine spikes as
Daniel pink says in his book drive the
single biggest motivator by far is
making progress on meaningful work
however the opposite is also true when
you aren't making progress on meaningful
work scientists have found that it can
be the single largest drain on
motivation so in short momentum is the
best feeling for high performers but a
lack of momentum is the opposite so
spending time without making significant
progress is draining mediocrity breeds
more mediocrity and then of course
there's the most obvious cost which is
the opportunity cost the longer it takes
you to achieve your goal the greater the
opportunity cost the extra time you
spend developing the skill is time taken
away from earning with it it's also time
that you could be spending on something
more productive if you're not making
progress with your trading you see the
truth is most Traders won't put in
enough effort into their development and
they'll never achieve their goal at all
they'll pay the cost but never achieve
any reward so think about this if you're
going to be spending time on your
trading anyway why not use that time as
effectively as possible as we've just
discussed a simple cost benefit analysis
shows us that giving it our rle giving
it 100% trying to do an exceptional job
is the much better deal here in fact I
have a great example of this with the
members in our community we run
something called the monthly
transformation contest and I'll explain
more about this in the next video and
how it works or you can check the link
in the description to watch our master
class and learn more about the way we
approach things here but basically we
give our members a guide for planning
how they can make a dramatic Improvement
in their trading over the next month in
a way that's focused and measurable and
we make it a bit of a competition to see
who plans and executes the best
transformation and that person wins a
prize now this process has revealed
something really interesting some
members follow the steps perfectly they
identify a specific area they need to
improve they set a plan with clear
actions to directly develop that area
they specify ways to objectively measure
their progress and then they give 100%
focus and effort during their sessions
but on the other hand some members
either don't spend as much time planning
things meticulously they don't approach
it in a realistic way or they don't see
the point or can't be bothered to think
things through in detail so they just
end up with a vague plan that basically
just leads them to going through the
motions and doing what they'd normally
do any other time for that month rather
than committing themselves to specific
actions they leave it open-ended so they
can basically do what they want and
that's what I see most other Traders
doing all the time but here's the thing
by the end of that transformation month
there's a huge difference in the level
of results we see members from the first
group achieving big Transformations
their well-thought out plan and focused
efforts leads them to making huge
strides towards their goals and having
noticeably better results whereas those
in the second group end up having a
fairly regular month maybe they've made
some progress but they're often not able
to tell whether they've made any more
progress than normal both groups used
more or less the same amount of time as
they usually would but those who spent
time creating a very effective plan and
then focusing their efforts in the right
areas and giving it their absolute all
were able to benefit massively and
transform their trading and those who
didn't it seems quickly realized the
error of their ways and approach the
next monthly transformation contest in
the right way as the old saying goes if
something's worth doing it's worth doing
well remember the cost of mediocrity is
far higher than the price of Excellence